Guide to the Fourth Internationalist Tendency Records TAM.156
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fourth Internationalist Tendency Records
1984-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fourth Internationalist Tendency (Group)
Le Blanc, Paul, 1947-
TAM.156
2.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Fourth Internationalist Tendency (FIT) was formed in 1983, by a group of individuals who split from the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) and who went on to publish the Bulletin in Defense of Marxism. FIT disbanded in 1992, its members merging into another Trotskyist organization, Solidarity. The collection includes internal bulletins, minutes, and correspondence; it also contains some SWP internal documents, bulletins of a British Trotskyist organization, the Socialist League, and materials produced by the Fourth International.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Paul Le Blanc in 1993. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.172.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically. The collection is organized in one series:
Missing Title
Series I: General Files, 1984-1992.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Fourth Internationalist Tendency (FIT) was a Trotskyist organization formed in 1983 after a factional split within the Socialist Workers Party (SWP). In the period 1981-1983 a number of leading members of the SWP, including George Breitman and Frank Lovell, created dissident factions within the Party and were soon expelled. Among the issues involved were differences over the SWP's turn toward "Castroism" and the question of affiliation and cooperation with the Fourth International. A 1982 speech by SWP leader Jack Barnes, "Their Trotsky and Ours," led to further defections and expulsions. A group of expelled members, led by Breitman and Lovell, went on to form the FIT in 1983. Other founding members of FIT included Paul Le Blanc, Evelyn Sell and Steve Bloom. Although expelled, the group considered itself an "external faction" of the SWP, and continued to try and influence the Party, without noticeable success. In 1990 the SWP, long estranged from the Fourth International, finally withdrew from the international body. This development caused the FIT to reassess its relationship to the SWP. The result was that the FIT disbanded in 1992 and merged with another Trotskyist organization, Solidarity, in 1993.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Breitman Papers (TAM 169)
Frank Lovell Papers (TAM 204)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, minutes, reports and internal bulletins produced by the Fourth Internationalist Tendency (FIT) and by other socialist groups working, both U.S. and foreign. Material and ephemera from FIT-sponsored events and projects are also found in the collection. Among these events are a 50th Anniversary celebration for the Fourth International, the "Moscow Trials Campaign," national conferences and speaking tours. In addition to various internal bulletins relating to FIT there is the FIT Information Letter, a short and frequently produced, multi-page newsletter highlighting recent activity within the organization, along with relevant mainstream news stories and announcements of events and demonstrations happening in the cities that the FIT had a presence in. Correspondence files include requests from the public for material about FIT. Paul Le Blanc, Evelyn Sell and Steve Bloom are primarily responsible for correspondence present in the collection, both internal communications and communications with other left groups.
Reports.; Programs (documents); Fliers (printed matter); Correspondence.; Bulletins.; Socialism -- United States -- 20th century.; New York (State); Communism -- United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Sell, Evelyn; Lovell, Frank; Le Blanc, Paul, 1947-; Fourth Internationalist Tendency (Group); Solidarity (Organization: U.S.); Socialist Workers Party; Fourth International
- Series I: General Files, 1984-1992.
  - Alliance for Socialist Action: Bulletins, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bloom, Steve: Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee to Defend Michael Warshawsky and the Alternative Information Center, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coordinating Committee for a U.S. Open Trotskyist Conference, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - FIT Educational Bulletin, Jul 1992-Aug 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - FIT Information Bulletin, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - FIT Information Letter, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - FIT Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - FIT Internal Information Bulletin, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - FIT Internal Information Bulletin, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - FIT Internal Information Bulletin, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - FIT Internal Information Bulletin, Jan 1992-Apr 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - FIT Internal Information Bulletin, Mat 1992-Aug 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FIT Women's Liberation Commission: Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fourth International Caucus of Solidarity, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fourth International Executive Committee: Correspondence, Reports, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fourth International: 50th Anniversary, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fourth International United Secretariat Bureau: Correspondence, Reports, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Information Requests and Replies, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - International Executive Committee: Reports, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - International Executive Committee: Women's Commission: Correspondence, Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Labor Party Advocates: Bulletins, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Labor Party Club: Proposal, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Le Blanc, Paul: Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: Cincinnati, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: Cleveland, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: Los Angeles, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: New York, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: New York Executive Committee, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: Pittsburgh, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Local Coordinators Minutes: Twin Cities, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Local Coordinators: New York, Correspondence, Fliers, Reports, 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mark Curtis Defense Committee: Fliers, Court Documents, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Marxist Education Bulletin: Correspondence, Bulletin, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Moscow Trials Campaign, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Conference: Cleveland, Ohio, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Conference: Cleveland, Ohio, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - National Conference: Fifth National Conference, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Conference: Oberlin College, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Conference: Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Conference: Wilder Forest, Minnesota, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Conference: Wilder Forest, Minnesota, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Conference: Wilder Forest, Minnesota -- Sunday Plenum, Sep 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Organizing Coordinators: Correspondence, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Organizing Coordinators: Minutes, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - National Organizing Coordinators: Minutes, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - National Organizing Committee Plenum, Feb 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - National Organizing Committee Plenum: Minutes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Partido Revolucionario de los Trabajadores (Mexico): Correspondence, Bulletins, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Regroupment Center Convention, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Samary, Catherine: Speaking Tour, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sell, Evelyn: Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Socialist Action Convention Reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Socialist Action: Correspondence, Reports, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Socialist League (UK): Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Socialist League (UK): Pre-Conference Discussion Bulletins, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Socialist Unity: Correspondence, Fliers, undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Socialist Workers Party (USA): Correspondence, Reports, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Solidarity: Bulletins, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Solidarity: Correspondence, Reports, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Solidarity Discussion Bulletin: Pre-Convention Series, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity Discussion Bulletin: Pre-Convention Series, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Solidarity Discussion Bulletin: Pre-Convention Series, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Trotskyist League: Correspondence, Reports, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)